<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[DevVault]]></title><description><![CDATA[Obsidian digital garden]]></description><link>http://github.com/dylang/node-rss</link><image><url>lib/media/favicon.png</url><title>DevVault</title><link></link></image><generator>Webpage HTML Export plugin for Obsidian</generator><lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2025 05:57:28 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="lib/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2025 05:57:27 GMT</pubDate><ttl>60</ttl><dc:creator></dc:creator><item><title><![CDATA[Roger Scruton - Chapter 2]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>In the chapter Resentment in Britain: Hobsbawm and Thompson from Thinkers of the New Left, Roger Scruton examines the ideas and works of two influential British Marxist historians, Eric Hobsbawm and E.P. Thompson. Scruton’s analysis is centered on what he perceives to be the deeper motivations, methods, and ideological commitments behind their historical scholarship, with a particular focus on how resentment shapes their worldview and intellectual output.<br>
<br>The Role of Resentment in Marxist Historiography<br>
Scruton begins by identifying the core emotional and intellectual driver of Hobsbawm and Thompson's work: resentment. According to Scruton, both historians are motivated not merely by an interest in historical truth but by a desire to right perceived wrongs inflicted by capitalism and the ruling class. This resentment is framed as a central aspect of their Marxist outlook, which seeks to reinterpret history through the lens of class struggle, painting the ruling classes in a negative light while celebrating the oppressed working class.
<br>Analysis and Example:<br>
Scruton argues that the emotional core of Marxist historiography is not just an objective investigation into the past, but a kind of moral crusade aimed at vindicating the working class. He points out that this predisposition skews their interpretations of historical events. For instance, in Hobsbawm’s work, Scruton sees an unrelenting hostility toward any historical development that doesn't align with a Marxist narrative. Hobsbawm, for example, presents capitalist developments such as industrialization not as complex historical processes but as inherently oppressive forces that stifled genuine human freedom.<br>Scruton's Critique:<br>
Scruton challenges the idea that resentment can serve as a valid basis for historical analysis. By interpreting history primarily as a struggle between oppressors and oppressed, Scruton argues, Hobsbawm and Thompson reduce the complexity of human motivations and social transformations. In this way, they oversimplify historical events by imposing a moral framework rather than seeking the truth in all its messiness.<br>
<br>Eric Hobsbawm’s Marxist Vision of History<br>
Scruton dives deeper into the work of Eric Hobsbawm, particularly focusing on his Marxist interpretation of historical events. Hobsbawm’s major works, such as The Age of Revolution, The Age of Capital, and The Age of Empire, reflect a consistent Marxist analysis that frames historical progress as the result of class struggle. Scruton contends that Hobsbawm is primarily concerned with demonstrating that capitalism is not a natural system but an artificial construct that imposes suffering on the majority for the benefit of a few.
<br>Example from Hobsbawm's Work:<br>
In Hobsbawm’s narrative of the Industrial Revolution, Scruton notes that he emphasizes the suffering of the working class while downplaying or ignoring the significant benefits that economic modernization brought to large sections of the population, such as improved living standards, technological innovation, and social mobility. For Hobsbawm, the story of industrial capitalism is primarily one of exploitation and alienation.<br>Scruton's Critique of Hobsbawm:<br>
Scruton argues that Hobsbawm’s Marxist methodology is not conducive to a fair or balanced historical account. His view of history is teleological, meaning that he interprets past events as part of an inevitable progression towards socialism. Scruton accuses Hobsbawm of being more interested in promoting a political agenda than in understanding the full range of human motivations behind historical events. This leads to a reductionist view of history, where economic and class interests are the only significant factors.<br>Moreover, Scruton criticizes Hobsbawm for his loyalty to communist regimes, particularly the Soviet Union, despite overwhelming evidence of their brutality and failure. Scruton sees this as evidence of Hobsbawm's ideological bias, which prevents him from acknowledging the moral and practical failures of Marxist systems.<br>
<br>E.P. Thompson and the 'Moral Economy'<br>
Moving on to E.P. Thompson, Scruton explores Thompson’s concept of the "moral economy," which he developed in his influential work The Making of the English Working Class. Thompson argues that pre-industrial communities operated according to a moral economy, where economic relations were embedded within social and moral expectations. The rise of capitalism, according to Thompson, destroyed this moral economy, replacing it with a system driven by profit and exploitation.
<br>Example from Thompson’s Work:<br>
Thompson’s analysis of the 18th-century food riots is a key example of this argument. He contends that these riots were not merely desperate acts by hungry people but were rooted in a collective sense of injustice. The rioters were defending traditional norms of fair pricing and access to basic goods, which they believed had been violated by greedy merchants and the capitalist system.<br>Scruton's Critique of Thompson:<br>
Scruton appreciates Thompson's skill as a historian but criticizes his romanticized view of the pre-industrial past. He argues that Thompson’s concept of a "moral economy" is idealized and oversimplified. In Scruton’s view, the pre-capitalist economy was not as moral or egalitarian as Thompson suggests, and the emergence of capitalism, while disruptive, brought about significant social and economic benefits.<br>Furthermore, Scruton challenges Thompson’s assumption that capitalism is inherently immoral. He points out that markets are, in fact, capable of producing moral outcomes, such as greater efficiency, wealth, and opportunities for social mobility. Scruton accuses Thompson of projecting his own ideological biases onto the past, thus distorting the historical record.<br>
<br>Historical Revisionism and Ideological Commitment<br>
Both Hobsbawm and Thompson, according to Scruton, are guilty of historical revisionism. Scruton argues that their commitment to Marxist ideology leads them to reinterpret historical events in ways that fit their ideological framework. This revisionism, Scruton claims, is not based on the pursuit of historical truth but on a desire to reshape the narrative in a way that justifies their political beliefs.
<br>Analysis:<br>
Scruton highlights that both historians selectively emphasize certain facts while ignoring others, depending on whether those facts support their Marxist interpretations. For example, they may highlight instances of class conflict while downplaying or ignoring instances of cooperation between classes. This selectivity, Scruton argues, distorts the historical record and presents a skewed view of the past.<br>Scruton's Broader Criticism of Marxist Historiography:<br>
At the heart of Scruton’s critique is the notion that Marxist historians like Hobsbawm and Thompson are not primarily interested in understanding history for its own sake. Instead, they are engaged in a form of ideological warfare, using history as a weapon to promote their political agenda. Scruton sees this as intellectually dishonest, as it undermines the historian’s duty to seek the truth, regardless of its political implications.<br>
<br>The Legacy of Hobsbawm and Thompson<br>
In conclusion, Scruton reflects on the lasting influence of Hobsbawm and Thompson on the intellectual left in Britain. Both historians, despite their biases and ideological commitments, have left a significant mark on the way history is taught and understood, particularly in the context of class struggle and capitalism.
<br>Scruton's Final Judgment:<br>
While Scruton acknowledges their intellectual contributions, he ultimately views their legacy as problematic. He argues that their work has encouraged a one-sided and overly negative view of capitalism, which continues to shape the thinking of many on the left. Their focus on resentment and victimhood, Scruton suggests, has led to a corrosive form of historical analysis that undermines a balanced understanding of the past.<br>In this chapter, Scruton presents a detailed critique of two of Britain’s most prominent Marxist historians. His key argument is that their work is shaped by an underlying resentment towards capitalism and the ruling class, which distorts their historical analysis. By prioritizing ideological commitment over objective truth, Hobsbawm and Thompson, according to Scruton, have contributed to a distorted and politicized view of history that continues to influence the intellectual left.<br><br>در فصل "کینه در بریتانیا: هابسبام و تامپسون" از کتاب متفکران چپ نو، راجر اسکروتن به بررسی ایده‌ها و آثار دو تاریخ‌نگار مارکسیست برجسته بریتانیایی، اریک هابسبام و ای.پی. تامپسون می‌پردازد. تحلیل اسکروتن بر انگیزه‌ها، روش‌ها و تعهدات ایدئولوژیکی آنان متمرکز است و به‌ویژه به نقش کینه در شکل‌گیری جهان‌بینی و آثار فکری‌شان توجه دارد.<br>1. نقش کینه در تاریخ‌نگاری مارکسیستی<br>اسکروتن بحث خود را با شناسایی عامل اصلی احساسی و فکری که کارهای هابسبام و تامپسون را هدایت می‌کند، یعنی کینه، آغاز می‌کند. به نظر او، این دو تاریخ‌نگار تنها به دنبال کشف حقیقت تاریخی نیستند، بلکه در پی جبران بی‌عدالتی‌هایی هستند که سرمایه‌داری و طبقات حاکم به وجود آورده‌اند. این کینه به‌عنوان بخشی اساسی از نگاه مارکسیستی آن‌ها، تاریخ را از دریچه مبارزه طبقاتی بازتعریف می‌کند و طبقات حاکم را به‌طور منفی و کارگران تحت ستم را به‌طور مثبت تصویر می‌کند.<br>تحلیل و مثال:<br>اسکروتن معتقد است که هسته احساسی تاریخ‌نگاری مارکسیستی تنها تحقیقاتی بی‌طرفانه در باب گذشته نیست، بلکه نوعی کارزار اخلاقی برای دفاع از طبقه کارگر است. او اشاره می‌کند که این پیش‌فرض، تفاسیر تاریخی آنان را تحریف می‌کند. به عنوان مثال، در کارهای هابسبام، اسکروتن دشمنی مداومی نسبت به هر توسعه تاریخی می‌بیند که با روایت مارکسیستی سازگار نیست. برای مثال، هابسبام صنعتی‌سازی را نه به‌عنوان یک فرایند پیچیده تاریخی، بلکه به‌عنوان نیرویی سرکوبگر که آزادی‌های واقعی انسانی را خفه کرده است، معرفی می‌کند.<br>انتقاد اسکروتن:<br>اسکروتن این دیدگاه را که کینه می‌تواند پایه‌ای معتبر برای تحلیل تاریخی باشد، به چالش می‌کشد. او معتقد است که با تفسیر تاریخ به‌عنوان مبارزه‌ای بین ستمگران و ستمدیدگان، هابسبام و تامپسون پیچیدگی‌های انگیزه‌های انسانی و تحولات اجتماعی را نادیده می‌گیرند. به این ترتیب، آن‌ها وقایع تاریخی را با اعمال چارچوبی اخلاقی ساده‌سازی می‌کنند، به‌جای آنکه به دنبال حقیقت در همه پیچیدگی‌هایش باشند.  <br>2. دیدگاه مارکسیستی اریک هابسبام نسبت به تاریخ<br>اسکروتن به‌طور خاص به بررسی آثار اریک هابسبام می‌پردازد و به تحلیل مارکسیستی او از رویدادهای تاریخی توجه می‌کند. آثار عمده هابسبام مانند عصر انقلاب، عصر سرمایه و عصر امپراتوری نشان‌دهنده تحلیلی مارکسیستی است که پیشرفت تاریخی را نتیجه مبارزه طبقاتی می‌داند. اسکروتن ادعا می‌کند که هابسبام به‌طور عمده به‌دنبال اثبات این نکته است که سرمایه‌داری یک سیستم طبیعی نیست، بلکه ساختاری مصنوعی است که بر اکثریت جامعه رنج تحمیل می‌کند تا اقلیتی سود ببرند.  <br>مثال از آثار هابسبام:<br>در روایت هابسبام از انقلاب صنعتی، اسکروتن اشاره می‌کند که او به‌طور عمده به رنج طبقه کارگر توجه می‌کند و مزایای مهمی را که نوسازی اقتصادی به بخش‌های وسیعی از جامعه آورده، مانند بهبود استانداردهای زندگی، نوآوری‌های تکنولوژیکی و تحرک اجتماعی، نادیده می‌گیرد. برای هابسبام، داستان سرمایه‌داری صنعتی در درجه اول داستانی از استثمار و بیگانگی است.  <br>انتقاد اسکروتن از هابسبام:<br>اسکروتن معتقد است که روش مارکسیستی هابسبام برای تاریخ‌نگاری منجر به ارائه‌ای ناعادلانه و غیرمتعادل از تاریخ می‌شود. دیدگاه هابسبام نسبت به تاریخ تلئولوژیک است، به این معنا که او رویدادهای گذشته را به‌عنوان بخشی از پیشرفت اجتناب‌ناپذیر به‌سوی سوسیالیسم تفسیر می‌کند. اسکروتن او را متهم می‌کند که بیش از آنکه به درک انگیزه‌های متنوع انسانی در رویدادهای تاریخی علاقه‌مند باشد، به دنبال پیشبرد یک دستور کار سیاسی است. این رویکرد، به نظر اسکروتن، به یک دیدگاه تقلیل‌گرایانه از تاریخ منجر می‌شود که در آن تنها عوامل اقتصادی و طبقاتی اهمیت دارند.<br>علاوه بر این، اسکروتن از وفاداری هابسبام به رژیم‌های کمونیستی، به‌ویژه اتحاد جماهیر شوروی، انتقاد می‌کند. با وجود شواهد گسترده‌ای از خشونت و شکست این رژیم‌ها، هابسبام به حمایت از آن‌ها ادامه داد. اسکروتن این وفاداری را نشانه‌ای از تعصب ایدئولوژیک هابسبام می‌داند که مانع از پذیرش شکست‌های اخلاقی و عملی سیستم‌های مارکسیستی توسط او می‌شود.  <br>3. ای.پی. تامپسون و "اقتصاد اخلاقی"<br>در ادامه، اسکروتن به بررسی مفهوم "اقتصاد اخلاقی" تامپسون می‌پردازد، مفهومی که او در اثر تأثیرگذار خود شکل‌گیری طبقه کارگر انگلیس توسعه داده است. تامپسون استدلال می‌کند که جوامع پیشاصنعتی بر اساس یک اقتصاد اخلاقی عمل می‌کردند، جایی که روابط اقتصادی در چارچوب انتظارات اجتماعی و اخلاقی قرار داشتند. ظهور سرمایه‌داری، به گفته تامپسون، این اقتصاد اخلاقی را نابود کرد و سیستمی مبتنی بر سود و استثمار را جایگزین آن کرد.  <br>مثال از آثار تامپسون:<br>تحلیل تامپسون از شورش‌های غذایی قرن هجدهم نمونه‌ای کلیدی از این استدلال است. او ادعا می‌کند که این شورش‌ها صرفاً اقدامات ناامیدانه‌ای از سوی مردم گرسنه نبودند، بلکه ریشه در یک حس جمعی از بی‌عدالتی داشتند. شورشیان در واقع از هنجارهای سنتی قیمت‌گذاری عادلانه و دسترسی به کالاهای اساسی دفاع می‌کردند که به باور آن‌ها توسط بازرگانان حریص و سیستم سرمایه‌داری نقض شده بود.  <br>انتقاد اسکروتن از تامپسون:<br>اسکروتن مهارت تامپسون به‌عنوان یک تاریخ‌نگار را می‌پذیرد، اما دیدگاه رمانتیک او نسبت به گذشته پیشاصنعتی را به چالش می‌کشد. او معتقد است که مفهوم "اقتصاد اخلاقی" تامپسون ایده‌آل‌سازی شده و بیش از حد ساده‌سازی شده است. به‌نظر اسکروتن، اقتصاد پیشاسرمایه‌داری به آن اندازه که تامپسون ادعا می‌کند، اخلاقی یا برابر نبود و ظهور سرمایه‌داری، هرچند مخرب، فواید اجتماعی و اقتصادی قابل توجهی به همراه داشت.<br>علاوه بر این، اسکروتن فرض تامپسون مبنی بر اینکه سرمایه‌داری ذاتاً غیراخلاقی است را به چالش می‌کشد. او تأکید می‌کند که بازارها در واقع قادر به تولید نتایج اخلاقی هستند، از جمله کارایی بیشتر، ثروت بیشتر و فرصت‌های تحرک اجتماعی. اسکروتن تامپسون را متهم می‌کند که پیش‌فرض‌های ایدئولوژیک خود را به گذشته تحمیل می‌کند و به این ترتیب، روایت تاریخی را تحریف می‌کند.  <br>4. بازنگری تاریخی و تعهد ایدئولوژیک<br>به گفته اسکروتن، هر دو هابسبام و تامپسون دچار بازنگری تاریخی هستند. اسکروتن استدلال می‌کند که تعهد آنان به ایدئولوژی مارکسیستی موجب می‌شود که رویدادهای تاریخی را به‌گونه‌ای تفسیر کنند که با چارچوب ایدئولوژیکی آنان سازگار باشد. این بازنگری، به عقیده اسکروتن، نه بر اساس جستجوی حقیقت تاریخی، بلکه با هدف بازآفرینی روایت تاریخی به‌گونه‌ای است که باورهای سیاسی آنان را توجیه کند.  <br>تحلیل:<br>اسکروتن برجسته می‌کند که هر دو تاریخ‌نگار برخی حقایق را برجسته می‌کنند و برخی دیگر را نادیده می‌گیرند، بسته به اینکه آیا آن حقایق از تفاسیر مارکسیستی آنان حمایت می‌کنند یا خیر. برای مثال، آن‌ها ممکن است به مواردی از درگیری طبقاتی توجه کنند و موارد همکاری میان طبقات را نادیده بگیرند. به گفته اسکروتن، این گزینش‌گری، سابقه تاریخی را تحریف کرده و تصویری نادرست و منحرف از گذشته ارائه می‌دهد.  <br>انتقاد کلی اسکروتن از تاریخ‌نگاری مارکسیستی:<br>در مرکز انتقادهای اسکروتن این دیدگاه قرار دارد که تاریخ‌نگاران مارکسیست مانند هابسبام و تامپسون در درجه اول به درک تاریخ برای خودش علاقه‌مند نیستند. بلکه، آن‌ها درگیر نوعی جنگ ایدئولوژیک هستند و از تاریخ به‌عنوان ابزاری برای پیشبرد اهداف سیاسی خود استفاده می‌کنند. اسکروتن این کار را به‌عنوان امری غیرصادقانه از نظر فکری در نظر می‌گیرد، زیرا وظیفه اصلی یک تاریخ‌نگار باید جستجوی حقیقت باشد، بدون توجه به اینکه این حقیقت چه تأثیرات سیاسی‌ای داشته باشد.<br>5. میراث هابسبام و تامپسون<br>در پایان، اسکروتن به تأثیر ماندگار هابسبام و تامپسون بر چپ فکری در بریتانیا اشاره می‌کند. با وجود تعصبات و تعهدات ایدئولوژیکی آنان، این دو تاریخ‌نگار تأثیر قابل توجهی بر نحوه تدریس و درک تاریخ گذاشته‌اند، به‌ویژه در زمینه مبارزه طبقاتی و سرمایه‌داری.  <br>داوری نهایی اسکروتن:<br>در حالی که اسکروتن سهم فکری آنان را می‌پذیرد، او در نهایت میراث آنان را مشکل‌زا می‌داند. او استدلال می‌کند که آثار آنان دیدگاهی یک‌جانبه و بیش از حد منفی از سرمایه‌داری ترویج کرده است که همچنان بر تفکر بسیاری از افراد چپ‌گرا تأثیر می‌گذارد. تمرکز آنان بر کینه و قربانی شدن، به گفته اسکروتن، به شکلی مخرب از تحلیل تاریخی منجر شده است که فهم متوازن گذشته را تضعیف می‌کند.<br>در این فصل، اسکروتن به‌طور مفصل به نقد دو تن از برجسته‌ترین تاریخ‌نگاران مارکسیست بریتانیا می‌پردازد. استدلال اصلی او این است که آثار آنان تحت تأثیر کینه‌ای عمیق نسبت به سرمایه‌داری و طبقه حاکم قرار دارد که موجب تحریف تحلیل تاریخی‌شان می‌شود. با اولویت‌بندی تعهد ایدئولوژیک بر جستجوی حقیقت عینی، هابسبام و تامپسون به گفته اسکروتن، به یک نگاه تحریف‌شده و سیاسی شده از تاریخ دامن زده‌اند که همچنان بر چپ فکری تأثیرگذار است.]]></description><link>Roger Scruton - Chapter 2.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Roger Scruton - Chapter 2.md</guid><pubDate>Sat, 04 Jan 2025 03:15:02 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>